All right.
Let's get started.
So last time, Tatsu
talked about scaling laws,
and we're going to take
a little break from that
and talk about an inference.
So the problem of
inference is very simple.
You've trained a model,
and you're given a prompt,
and you want to produce
the response usually
as accurately and as
quickly as you can.
So inference turns out
to be only one lecture,
but it's actually of
growing importance.
And it shows up in many places.
So clearly, once
you've trained a model,
you don't just sit there.
And if you're a
researcher, you put
a plot in your paper of
here's how my model works,
but for everyone else, you
actually want to use this model.
So what does use look like?
It could be chatting with
an AI assistant or chatbot,
it could be doing
code completion.
These days, agents
are very popular,
and that requires inference.
Batch data processing as well.
It's also used for evaluation.
For evaluation that requires
generation in particular.
And it's also used
inside training.
If you're doing
reinforcement learning,
you need to have a model,
you generate rollouts,
and you score them, and
you update the weights
appropriately.
So inference shows up
all over the place.
And efficiency, as is
the theme of this class,
really matters more
than ever here.
And even if you just look at the
actual use app of vantage point,
training is a one-time cost.
It could be very expensive.
It is very expensive.
But once you're done
with it, that's it.
But inference is
a repeated cost.
You kind of incur
them every single day.
So OpenAI is
estimated to produce
8.6 trillion tokens a day.
And just for
reference, DeepSeek-V4,
which came out
earlier this year,
was trained on 32
trillion tokens.
So in less than four
days, the number of tokens
that OpenAI has to produce,
and therefore the compute
is at least DeepSeek-V4.
And of course, even
the frontier models
might be trained on
more tokens, but still,
inference, the number of tokens
generated is going to be higher.
So that's just some perspective.
And moreover, I think the
importance of inference
has grown in the last year
because once upon a time,
we thought of language
models as primarily
as chatbots or assistants,
where you put in a prompt,
you get back a response,
and presumably,
the goal of the human
is to read the response.
But now, as we move more
into a genetic world,
what it looks like is
that a query goes in,
and the agent is going
to do a bunch of stuff.
It's going to think,
it's going to reason,
it's going to call some tools,
it's going to introspect.
And at the end of the day,
it will produce some output
for a human to read.
So most of the tokens
that the agent produces
is actually not for reading.
And so you should really
think about the number
of tokens generated as
really the compute spend.
And there's no limit.
If you have an ambitious
enough problem,
you're going to need much
compute and a lot of tokens.
So if you were in
the chatbot world,
maybe inference after
a certain point,
it's fast enough, because
humans can only read so fast.
But for an agent, there's
no limit to how much a value
you can get out of squeezing
more out of inference.
So there's a lot of
people doing inference
on the commercial side.
Of course, all the
closed API providers
have to serve their
models, so inference
is a big deal for them.
And there is also a
bunch of providers
serving open weight models and
providing inference as well.
And in the open
source community,
there's a bunch of packages.
So VLM is probably
a popular one.
Kind of a go-to.
SG Lang is another one
that's particularly
good for agentic workloads,
but maybe not as popular yet.
And then there's TensorRT from
NVIDIA, which is really fast,
but it's more narrow.
And then Llama CPP, if you
want to run inference on CPU,
this is a popular package.
So hopefully, I've argued
that inference is huge.
If you can make inference twice
as fast or even 10% faster,
that is a big deal.
So now, the question
is, what does fast mean?
So there's a few metrics that
capture the notion of fast.
And they're going to be
applicable in different settings
and have different trade offs.
So one metric of fast is
time to first token or TTFT.
This is essentially
how long a user waits
before any generation happens.
So you put in a
query into ChatGPT,
and some number of milliseconds
passes by, and then
from the point the first token
comes in, that is the time.
And this is generally useful
for interactive applications
because that latency where
you're just waiting and doing
nothing is--
the longer that is, the
worse the user experience,
and as soon as tokens
come in, it doesn't maybe
have to be that fast, because if
you're going to read it anyway,
you can't read that fast.
So the second metric is latency.
And this is from the standpoint
of an individual user.
How fast are tokens
appearing for one query?
This is also important for
interactive applications.
So basically, this is how fast
the tokens are kind of streaming
through.
And then the second
related concept
is throughput, measuring
tokens per second,
this is how fast tokens are
appearing for many queries.
So latency or one
latency and throughput
are clearly very related.
It's very kind of
aligned-- in general,
many interventions will make
latency and throughput better.
But as we'll see later, there's
actually a trade off here.
And throughput is useful
for if you're doing
a bunch of batch processing.
You have a petabyte
of data, and you
want to process it
with a language model.
You just want that
job to get done.
It doesn't matter if one query
is coming in faster, sooner,
or later.
OK.
So what determines
the efficiency
by either any of these
metrics of inference.
So the high level
bit is as follows.
And this is-- maybe
one high level bit
to remember from the lecture is
that when you're doing training,
you see all the tokens
at once, because
in supervised fine-tuning,
you see all the tokens,
and you can parallelize
over the sequence.
Remember, think about
in the transformer,
the calculation
for attention, MLP,
the sequence is
just a dimension.
So it's a big tensor
that gets multiplied.
And so you, essentially,
process all the tokens at once.
In inference, you can't do that.
You have to generate because
of the autoregressive nature
of inference.
Tokens sequentially.
One at a time.
So this is the
fundamental problem
of why inference is a
very different workload
than training, because you can't
parallelize across the sequence
dimension.
And therefore, as
we'll see later,
it's going to be harder to
have high arithmetic intensity
or fully utilize the compute.
OK.
All right.
So let's go on.
So first, I'm going to-- just
maybe a preview of what's
in this lecture.
First, I'm going to do some math
to understand the arithmetic
intensity and
throughput and latency,
how to think about
that for a transformer.
And then I'm going to talk
about various techniques
to reduce the cost by
making the kv cache smaller,
quantizing model
pruning, and then
finally, I'll talk about
speculative decoding, and then
some kind of practical concerns.
All right.
So this is going to be a
bit of a review, mostly
kind of swapping in,
making sure we're
on the same page with
respect to notation.
Much of this lecture is based
on the scaling book from Google
on transformers and inference.
So I do recommend that
people go check it out.
It's a very nicely written.
And some of the
figures are generously
lifted from that book.
OK.
So just to establish
a bit of notation
to understand this diagram.
So we're going to use symbols.
Think about it in ienops
to denote dimensions,
but also they're kind of length.
So B is going to be the
batch dimension and also
the number of sequences.
T is going to be the
sequence dimension, which
is also the number of tokens.
D is the model dimension,
H is the dimension.
So if I'm going to
write this, this
is taking a product between a
tensor with dimensions B, T,
and D, and another matrix of
D and H, and I produce BTH.
So what is going on
here is that there
are some dimensions
marked red, which
are going to be contracting.
These dimensions appear
in both the operands
and disappear from the results.
And then there's going to
be other regular dimensions
in black that appear only in one
operand and stay in the result.
So this is the general form.
Another case is if you
have blue dimensions, that
means they're
attaching dimensions,
and they appear in both,
but stay in the result.
They do not get
contracted or reduced.
OK.
So the interpretation
here, as we'll see later,
is that we have this
tensor for every sequence
and token position.
You have a vector and you want
to multiply that by a matrix.
And then here, you're
basically taking
a bunch of dot products
between two tensors.
OK.
So with that in mind, this
in all its full glory,
is the description of
a transformer block.
So it looks a little bit
like a circuit diagram.
There's a lot of details
here, but I actually
find this probably the
most crisp definition
of what a transformer is.
You see a lot of
description of transformer,
and frankly, a lot
of them are-- it's
hard to understand what
is exactly happening.
This one basically tells
you exactly the shapes
of the tensors and allows you
to reason about the dependency.
So for transformer
block, you take
the X, which is the
activations of one layer,
you feed it through
a tension, and then
you feed it through MLP.
And just as a kind
of a quick refresher,
you projected using a query
matrix, a key matrix and a value
matrix, you'll see
here that we have
N, which is the
number of heads, and H
is the dimension of each head.
So the query matrix is batch
times sequence times number
of heads times the
head dimension,
and K and V,
instead of having N,
we have K, which
we'll see later,
which we have a potentially
smaller number key value heads.
And then this is the
attention operation,
where notice that there's
batching dimensions.
So B appears in both.
And we're contracting
over the head dimension.
And we'll come back to
why this B, B in both,
makes inference hard.
Why attention is kind
of a bottleneck there.
So just hold on to that thought.
And the MLP is very simple
and straightforward.
You just do some math models.
This is the gating matrix.
This is the upper direction
and a down projection.
So thank you guys.
I have implemented this.
So I don't want to
belabor it, but just
to swap in the notation.
By convention, we're going
to assume that in the MLP,
the MLP up projects the D
dimensional, model dimension
into four times that.
So F is always--
think about it as 4D
whenever you see F.
And then the model dimension
gets split across the N heads.
So the model dimension is
always equal to number of heads
times the head dimension.
And then the number
of heads get split,
in the case of group
query attention,
into the number of groups and
the number of heads per group.
And finally, we have
two variables, S and T,
which both represents
the sequence dimension.
And the difference
is that S is going
to represent the
number of input tokens,
and T is going to represent
the number of output tokens.
So in training time,
these two are the same,
because we're predicting all
the same inputs as outputs.
And inference time,
T is going to be 1,
and S is going to be the input.
OK.
So another review for
arithmetic intensity.
So I talked about this
in the second lecture.
So just as a warm up.
Suppose I'm multiplying
two matrices; a B by D
matrix and a D by F matrix.
So intuition.
B is the batch dimension,
D is the hidden dimension
or the model dimension, and
F is the projection dimension
in the MLP.
So remember, what are
the arithmetic intensity?
I have to count
flops, and I have
to count the amount
of memory moved.
So we can do this as follows.
So what do you have to do
to multiply these matrices?
Now, remember, the
systems, lectures,
you have to read X from HBM.
And if you're storing
everything in bf16,
which is the case
for inference, we're
going to have 2 times B times D,
you're going to read W. That's
going to be another
2 times D times F.
You're going to do the matmul.
So that's number of flops
is 2 times B times D times F
And then you're going
to write it back.
OK?
So every time you
read and write,
it's basically the
number of entries.
It's kind of a quadratic-like
term, and matmuls are qubit.
And remember, this is
going to be important
because that's how you're
going to get high arithmetic
intensity.
So total number of
flops is the cubic,
and then the bytes transferred
is the sum of the reads
and writes.
So remember, arithmetic
intensity is how much compute
we do per byte transfer.
And we want this to be high.
So the intensity is going
to be equal to flops
over bytes transfer.
And I'm representing all
these things symbolically,
because it will be
easier to see and work
with rather than numbers.
One just simplification
we can make
is that suppose that
the batch dimension here
is much less than D and F,
then we can simplify this.
So in particular, what this
is doing is saying D equals C
times D and F equals C times
B and let C goes to infinity,
so both D and F are really
large and B is smaller,
and this just reduces
to the intensity of B.
So the upshot of
that is that remember
when we did arithmetic
intensity for matmul,
it was something like N/3.
And this is the kind
of analog, where
instead of just having
square matrices,
we have non-square matrices.
OK.
So just to compare, so
the accelerator intensity
of a hardware is you look
at the flops per second
in the spec sheet, you look at
how much memory bandwidth, how
fast memory gets moved
between HBM, you divide,
and that is the
accelerated intensity.
And now, you compare your
computations intensity
with your accelerator intensity.
And if it's greater then your
compute bound, which is good,
if you're less, then you're
memory bound, and that's bad.
So in this case, for H100,
for this particular matmul
operation, you're compute
bound if the batch
size is greater than 295.
So here's an extreme case.
So suppose you just
have one example.
What happens is you
have one example, then
your arithmetic intensity
is going to be one.
And this is going
to be memory bound.
And you can see
what's going on here.
You're reading this DF
matrix, but B is only one.
So you're effectively doing
only 2 times D times F flops.
And this is basically
the workload
that you'll see in inference.
You don't get these
full matrices,
you get these very thin
matrices or tensors.
OK.
Let me stop there in case
there's any questions.
Yeah.
In the transformer slide, I just
want to confirm [INAUDIBLE].
You said, across [INAUDIBLE]
can search across [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, should that be across
tables instead of cubes?
Let's see.
So the number of
groups here is--
wait, I'm just making sure.
So K is the number
key value heads.
And so you have g per KV head.
My understanding is [INAUDIBLE]
each key path will have one
[INAUDIBLE] correspond to it.
And [INAUDIBLE] then g is
the number of [INAUDIBLE] p.
That means we have k.
That's my question.
Yeah, OK.
Yeah, I think you're right.
So k should be the
number of groups,
and g should be the number
of the heads per one
of those groups.
Yes.
Yeah, OK.
Thanks for that.
I'll fix that later.
OK.
So let's talk a little bit
more about the arithmetic
intensity of inference.
So here's how to think about
what's happening in inference.
Let's say you just
do it naively.
So here is a prompt
never going to give you.
I'm going to the transformer.
And the transformer does
generates keys and values
and activations.
And at the end of the
day, it generates logits
over the output vocabulary.
And you sample a
token, and that token
gets concatenated
with the prompt,
and then you just do this again.
You generate never.
You attach that to the prompt
and so on and so forth.
So this is the most naive thing.
If you have a black box
that takes a sequence
and outputs a distribution
over tokens, which
is exactly what a
transformer does,
you can just apply
this repeatedly.
OK, so this works, but this is
really bad because each time you
generate one token,
you actually take
order T squared time where
T is the number of tokens
that you've generated so far.
So generate T tokens is actually
T cubed because the attention is
already T squared, and you have
to do that once for every token.
So this is pretty bad,
but the observation
is that you don't
actually have to do this.
A lot of the work can actually
be shared across prefixes.
So for example, if you're over
generating network versus you're
generating up, you're
actually computing
a lot of the same key values
for never going to give.
So these tokens, they
shouldn't change, OK?
And this is because it's
a causal transformer.
If it was bidirectional,
then if you attach a token,
then everything changes.
But if it's causal,
then the activations
here don't change based
on any tokens you append.
So with that observation,
the first obvious thing
is to store a KV
cache in HPM, so
that, between successive
token generations,
you can just reuse the KV cache.
So that means when you are
trying to generate gonna, you
don't actually have to compute
all the keys and activations
of these previous tokens.
So this is what it looks
like with a KV cache.
So there's going to be
two stages pre-fill.
So you get the prompt, and you
populate the KV cache, which
is the set key and value pairs
that the transformer computes,
and then you
generate the logit--
just the same computation
as we did before.
And now you have the KV cache
here and then this distribution
which you sample at a token.
And now you feed that through
the transformer, which
uses this cache
and then produces
both the distribution
of the next tokens,
but a new KB, which is
basically activations
corresponding to the token up.
And then this gets fed in.
So now you have the
command to KV cache.
You have this logits you
sample, and then that
feeds to the transformer.
You output the distribution
over next tokens
as well as the new token
which you add to the KB cache
and so on and so forth.
So the KV cache formula
is for every sequence--
so there's B of them.
For every token,
there's S of them.
And for every layer
and every head,
you store H dimensional vector.
And just to reiterate for
inference, there's prefill.
You given a prompt.
You encode the prompt
into these vectors.
And this is parallelizable
just like in training
because you see
the entire prompt.
You can compute the KV cache.
And then in generation, you
generate the new response tokens
sequentially.
But at least you
don't have to pay
for generating the KV
cache of the tokens
that you already looked at.
So is everyone comfortable
with the KV cache?
Any questions about this?
All right, so let's try to
figure out the FLOPs and memory
I/O for both MLP and
attention layers.
So remember S is
the number of tokens
we're kind of conditioning on,
and T is the number of tokens
we're generating.
So we're going to
do this abstractly.
And then later, we'll specify
to the prefill where T equals S,
and generation T equals 1.
So for the MLP layers--
and through all of this,
I'm just going to
look at the MAmmoTH
because the MAmmoTH
are the thing that
actually require a lot of work.
Everything else can
is not that many FLOPs
and can be potentially
fused into the MAmmoTH too.
OK.
So let's do this calculation.
So it's the same as the
matrix calculations.
I'm not going to maybe belabored
step through every single detail
here, but just the
form is you read X
from high bandwidth memory.
You read all the parameters.
You compute the
upper projection,
and then you write it to HBM.
You compute the gate,
and you write HBM,
and then you compute basically
the down projection of that,
and you write it to HBM.
So the number of flops
depends on B and T
and D and F. So batch
size, sequence length,
model dimension, and the
feedforward dimension,
MLP dimension.
And the bytes transferred
is this expression.
So now you can compute
the arithmetic intensity
which, again, is FLOPs
divided by bytes transferred.
So this is some expression.
We're going to assume, that
just like before, B times T
is much smaller than D and
F. And with that, then we see
that intensity is B times T.
So this is analogous to
just the MAmmoTH case.
There's more matrices and
there's more dimensions,
but fundamentally
it's the same thing.
And that makes sense.
An MLP is basically
a big MAmmoTH.
And it also makes sense
because the batch dimension
and the sequence
length dimension are--
everything is independent.
And for the MLP,
they don't interact.
Attention is different story.
And so B times T. So
as long as you have--
in the pre-fill, if
you make B times T
large enough-- large batches,
long sequences-- you'll be fine.
Now, let's look at generation.
So remember, generation,
there's two problems here.
One is that
generation T equals 1.
You're only generating
one token at a time.
And so that means your
arithmetic intensity
is going to be B,
but B in generation
is the number of
concurrent requests.
And so if you're in a batch
setting, you can control that.
But if you're, let's
say, serving a chatbot,
it's the number of
concurrent requests
is essentially how many users,
concurrent users there are?
Which can be high.
It be low.
So it's a bit unpredictable.
It can be changing over time.
So that's something we're
going to address when we
talk about continuous batching.
But overall, this is
not bad because as long
as you have large batches,
the sequence length
isn't going to really help you.
But if you have large
batches, you should be good.
So now let's look at
the attention layer.
So again, S is in the previous
tokens already generated.
T is the number of tokens you
want to generate logits for.
So in attention, you read
the QKV matrices from HPM.
You compute the attention.
You compute the softmax
which doesn't really matter,
and compute the value
matrix, and then you
write the result to HBM.
So the FLOPs is B times
S times T times D,
and the bytes transferred
is this expression.
Everything's is
a MAmmoTH, right?
So this should be always one
degree higher of a polynomial
than the bytes transferred
because it's a MAmmoTH.
The only question is, what
is that factor look like?
So that factor for attention
is S times T over S plus T.
So let's look at the prefill.
So prefill, what
this is saying is
that the prefill intensity
is S over 2 when T equals
S. So this is good, right?
Because as long as you have long
sequence lengths for attention,
you're going to maintain
high arithmetic intensity.
Notice that the batching
dimension doesn't happen here.
I'll explain a bit why later.
But for generation,
this is bad news.
So the generated nation
intensity is S over S plus 1,
and that's less than 1, or
even let's just call it 1.
And aromatic intensity,
remember 1 is bad.
We want it to be something
like 295 for H100
to be to saturate the compute.
And so this is really
the bottleneck.
So we did all this
analysis for MLP attention,
prefilled generation, and we've
found this to be a bottleneck.
So let's try to contemplate
why this is a bottleneck.
So unlike MLPs-- so MLP is
for generation is actually OK
as long as your sequence is--
sorry, your batch
is large enough.
So the problem with this
ML attention is that--
let's look at MLPs.
Every sequence hits
the same MLP weights.
So these don't depend on B.
Whereas, in attention layer,
each sequence has
its own KV cache.
So these all depend on MLP.
And so you can think about
this as what's going on here
is that in the MLP case,
having B being big actually
is helpful because you get to
load these MLP weights once.
And you can use it for
all your sequences.
That's how you get high
arithmetic intensity
because you use it--
simplifying a bit,
you load it once.
You do all your
batch processing,
and then that is good.
Whereas, in attention, all these
depend on B. So increasing B
doesn't help.
It's like for every
sequence, you're
basically doing a MAmmoTH.
So they're all independent.
So doing more MAmmoTHs
isn't helpful.
Just if you remember
in the very beginning,
I showed you this example.
This also has pretty bad
arithmetic intensity.
It's not a MAmmoTH
because we're essentially
batching by a coordinate.
And this is essentially
basically the same
as doing a dot product,
which has horrible arithmetic
intensity.
And remember, this
is in the attention.
This blue B is the cause
of why the attention is
arithmetic intensity
doesn't scale with B,
and why that is a bottleneck.
So just to summarize here.
So prefill is compute-bound.
Generation is memory-bound.
So if you look at the MLP
intensity for prefill,
it's B times S, great.
Prefill for attention,
intensity S over 2--
not as good, but workable.
Generation MLP
intensity, also workable,
requires long
concurrent requests.
But it is really the
generation attention
intensity which is a fundamental
bottleneck, and that's it.
If you're sticking
with a transformer,
you can't really improve this.
OK.
Pause there for questions.
So now whenever you hear
people say, oh, inference
is memory bound, you know why.
OK.
So let's now use these
intuitions and calculations
to think about our
inference metrics
throughput and
latency and also TFRT.
All right.
So inference is memory bound.
Now the main-- I
mean, in some ways
this simplifies a lot
of things because when
we think about how
long things take,
you just look at how much memory
needs to be transferred, OK?
Because assuming you overlap
communication and computation,
the bottleneck is going to
be just the amount of memory
that you have to deal with.
So in some ways, it's
nice because it's simpler.
But in other ways,
it's frustrating
that your accelerators
are sitting there not
doing anything.
So let's walk
through an example.
So for Llama 2.13B on an H100.
So what is the latency
and the throughput?
So remember Llama 2.13B
has a particular shape.
So this is a sequence
length, the model dimension,
feedforward dimension, number of
query, number key value heads.
There's no GQA here.
So the N equals
k, head dimension,
number of layers of vocab
size, and the memory bandwidth
for H100.
So now, using this
config, let's compute
the transformer
performance statistics, OK?
So these are our inputs here.
And just the statistics
I'm going to compute
are going to be number of
parameters, the memory, usage
latency, and throughput.
So first of all,
what takes memory?
So the parameters take memory.
So we compute the
number of parameters.
And so you look at the
embeddings, the MLP layers,
the projections of the KQV.
At the end of the day, you
get some number of parameters.
Assuming that we're doing
a bf16, which is always
the case for inference,
then parameters
take up this many bytes.
Also in memory is the KV cache.
And the KV cache is the number
of tokens in your sequence
times the number of heads and
the KV heads times the head
dimension times the
number of layers.
You have one for the key
and one for the value,
and then you have
multiple two for bf16.
So that's the size
of the KV cache.
And the total memory usage is--
this is for each sequence
you have B sequences.
So that's B times that
plus the parameter size.
And that's the amount
of memory you need.
And now, what's the latency?
The latency is determined
by the memory I/O, OK?
Because inference is
memory-bound, most assuming you
overlap communication
and compute.
All the memory, it's going to
be on shuffling parameters back
and forth between HPM and SRAM.
So that's how long it takes
to move memory around.
Throughput is the
inverse of latency,
but we're generating
B tokens in parallel.
So this is tokens per second.
This is seconds per token.
This is tokens per
second, as well as
having an additional B because
you're processing a batch of B.
So now, let's compute
for this config what
are these actual values?
So num parameters is 13 billion.
So a good sanity check-- that
is advertised as a 13 billion
parameter model.
Memory is this term, which
is about 838 million times B.
So it's basically
a linear function
of B plus some other term.
So this is a KV
cache which grows
as B. This is the
parameters, which
is double the number of params.
Now, latency is just this
scale by the memory bandwidth,
so it has the same
form as the memory.
And throughput is B over that.
So notice that latency,
as you increase B,
grows because the
KV cache grows.
And in order to
process stuff, you
have to copy the KV
cache back and forth.
And now, throughput
is more interesting
because, as you
increase B, throughput
does improve but up to a limit.
Throughput improves
because now you're
amortizing the cost
over a larger batch.
But also, the speed at which
you're processing this obviously
is also increasing over time.
So this asymptotes.
It's not going to--
throughput can't
possibly go to infinity.
Any questions about this so far?
So basically, you
just have to remember
latency is a linear function in
B. This is where the constant is
the size of KV
cache, and then this
is the number of parameters.
And then throughput is some
proportional to B over B
plus something.
So now, let's instantiate this
for a bunch of situations, OK?
So if you have batch size 1,
so this is what you would get.
You get a latency of
0.008 seconds per token.
And the throughput is
124 tokens per second.
So what happens if you
increase the batch size,
you'll see that the
latency goes up,
but the throughput also goes up.
So latency gets worse, but
the throughput improves.
So this is an interesting thing
because we think about, oh, we
just want to make it go fast.
But fast actually
has two meanings
here, which actually, depending
on which one you care about,
is completely opposite.
If you want to tune
your batch size,
that's going to really
determine if you
want latency or throughput.
And what happens if you
increase-- let's say, increase--
we really want high
throughput because we're
processing lots of documents.
Let's increase the batch
size even more, OK?
So the latency gets even worse.
I mean, yeah, it gets worse.
Throughput gets even better.
But the main problem here is
that your memory, you run out
of memory because the memory,
for storing this KV cache,
is going to exceed
your H100 memory.
And if you have B200s, you can
increase the batch size more,
but eventually you
hit some of limit.
So there's limitations
to how much
you can increase
your throughput.
You'll never get
to the asymptote
because you'll hit the memory.
And also, your
throughput is getting--
your gains are kind of
diminishing as well.
So increasing batch
size worsens the latency
because now you have a larger
KV cache to read and write.
And remember, it's batched.
So if you're an
individual query,
you have to wait for
everyone to finish.
So you have to basically--
you're waiting for a bus,
and the latency is pretty high.
You wait and then you go.
Whereas, the throughput
of a bus is pretty good
because you can move
everyone at once.
So the throughput improves
as batch size increases
because, remember, the
parameters are shared,
and you load that
once into memory.
And you can process
a lot of sequences.
So trade-off between
latency and throughput,
just to make sure everyone's
aligned-- smaller batch sizes
use better latency
but worse throughput.
Large batch sizes yield better
throughput but worse latency.
OK.
I'm not going to really talk
about parallelism too much.
There's also another
dimension of inference,
which is you can
shard your model
across multiple all devices.
You can look at the scaling
book chapter on inference
if you want to know more.
Just as a very trivial
example, if you
launch M copies of the model,
the latency is the same,
and the throughput
increases by M.
And then the other metric
we didn't talk about
is time to first token.
And this is
essentially the time it
takes to do prefill because
after you finish prefill,
then you can basically
start generating.
So if you want to fast--
if you want faster TTFT, you
should use smaller batch sizes,
and you want larger batch
sizes to improve throughput.
So hopefully, that is clear.
Any questions about
throughput and latency
and how their intention
with each other?
OK.
So now that we have a conceptual
framework for thinking
about how efficient inference is
in terms of arithmetic intensity
and throughput and latency, now
let's try to make it faster.
How do we make inference faster?
There's a bunch of
different techniques which
are quite varied, ranging from
changing the model architecture
to doing systems optimization
and everything in between.
So inference in some sense is a
fairly rich cross-cutting topic.
So the most maybe now in
hindsight obvious thing
you can think about is
hopefully beat it into your head
that memory is the
bottleneck for inference,
and the KV cache takes
up a lot of memory.
And it could even be larger
than the number of parameters
if for a large
enough batch size.
So let's just try to reduce
the size of the KV cache.
Now, you have to be careful
about how you do this
because you want to make
sure you don't lose too
much accuracy in the process.
So here is one thing you can do,
which we already talked about,
which is grouped
query attention.
And just as a reminder here,
so multi-headed attention--
basically for every
token, you have
a key and a value and a query.
And if you do grouped
query attention,
you basically compute the
same number of queries,
but you have only a
smaller number of groups,
and you compute key and
value for each group.
So K is the number
of groups here.
And so in the multi-headed
attention, K is N, no reduction.
There's something called multi
query attention, which no one
uses because it's really bad.
K equals 1.
And somewhere in
between is hopefully
where we'll find a balance
between accuracy and speed.
So this is the paper that
introduces GQA from 2023.
And they show that if you
look at time per sample, which
is related to both
latency and throughput,
you see that the MHA--
so Multi-Head Attention.
Full attention has
this high time.
Whereas, if you start K
equals 1, it's much faster.
And then you can actually
keep on increasing the K to K
equals 8, and it's
still pretty good.
And eventually, your
time goes up quite a bit.
OK.
So why does GQA improve
latency and throughput?
Well, it reduces the KV cache by
a factor of N over K. And just
as a friendly reminder, reducing
memory usage leads to speed up
because we're memory-bound.
So let's revisit our
friendly Llama model here.
Remember in the
initial configuration,
we're just using K
equals N. So there's
no multi-headed-- there's
multi-head attention,
no reduction in the
number key and values.
And so for this one, remember
using a batch size of 64,
we get this throughput
and latency.
Now if you do GQA, we're
going to put in, let's say,
a kind of a sparsity
of 1 one five.
That reduces the
memory quite a bit,
which, in turn,
improves the latency
and also improves
the throughput.
So it's not that latency and
throughput are always at odds.
If you reduce the amount of
memory, then it improves both.
It's mainly the batch
dimension that allows.
That is the point of tension.
OK.
So this is great.
And let's actually just increase
the batch size even more
and see what happens.
So before, if we had
a batch size of 256,
we ran out of memory.
But now, it fits in memory.
And we see that, the latency
suffers a bit because we're
increasing the batch
size, but the throughput
goes up proportionally.
So sometimes you play with
these parameters jointly.
You can reduce the
KV cache, but that
allows you to increase
the batch size
and allow making
other trade-offs.
So the final thing you
have to do whenever
you do some lossy
change is that you make
sure the accuracy doesn't drop.
And this paper shows that for
a GQA, the time is better.
But across a bunch of evals,
basically it works well.
So now with these
accuracy values,
I think you always have to
take it with a grain of salt
because this is for
a particular model.
Later, the deep sea paper should
show that it actually does hurt.
So I guess, take
everything that's
not just math with a
grain of salt here.
OK.
So speaking of DeepSeek,
here's another idea
to reduce the KV cache.
So the theme is reduce the KV
cache and latency and throughput
improve.
So this is
multi-headed attention,
same number of queries and keys
and values for every token.
And GQA, remember, we have
reduced the number of keys
and values for every token.
Sorry, not for every token.
We basically have reduced the
number of values and keys.
And now, the multi-latent
attention for DeepSeek
says we're actually going
to leave the number of keys
and values the same one for
every token essentially.
But I'm going to parameterize--
I'm going to compress these.
So normally, you have some--
how do you compute
your keys and values?
You have your activations,
and you multiply them
by some matrix to get K and
some other matrix to get V.
And these are generally N times
H dimensions, like your model
dim, which is big.
So MLA says I'm going
to actually project
these activations down
into C dimensions.
So DeepSeek-V2 reduced
it from 16,000 to 512,
so this is quite aggressive
compression here.
And then I'm going to
compute the k and the V
from this compressed
representation.
So now, I can just store
C. This is much smaller.
And then when I need
my keys and values,
I can just materialize them.
So there is one
wrinkle here, which
is that MLA is not
compatible with rope,
which operates directly
on the keys and values.
So what they do is add
additional dimensions
for handling the rope.
But more or less, it's still
a pretty big reduction.
So the latency and
throughput improvements
follow by just simple math.
The smaller the KV
cache, the faster you go.
It's almost kind of linear
scaling up until at some point.
And then, remember,
you need to check
whether your model is accurate.
So first of all,
this is the result
that kind of contradicts or is
in tension with the GQA paper.
They show that GQA
actually isn't that great.
So this is MHA.
This is GQA.
These numbers are smaller
than these numbers.
But they show that their method,
MLA, Multi-Latent Attention
works even a little
bit better than MHA.
But let's just say
it's about the same.
So this column and this
column are much better than--
I guess there's no
GQA on this table.
You have to compare over here.
So I'll show you an-- yeah.
How does this compare
to reducing the number
of dimensions, the model?
So the question
is, how does this
compare with reducing the
dimension of the model?
So that's a good question.
These ablations don't show that.
My guess is that reducing
the model dimension
just makes things worse
because you're indiscriminately
just reducing everything.
I think the trick in
all of this kind of
is to find places in the
model where you can squeeze.
And this apiary,
I don't think you
can necessarily know for sure.
You just have to do a
bunch of experimentation
and see what works.
So here's another idea
to reduce your KV cache.
This is called
cross-layer attention.
So the idea is that normally,
every layer has KV, K's and V's.
But let's say instead of
doing that, we're just
going to compute KVs for
a subset of the layers.
And then, just for
this layer, I'm
just going to use the
previous layers on KV cache.
So this is another
way of sharing.
Just like GQA shares
K across heads,
now I'm sharing
KVs across layers.
And empirically, this
paper shows that doing this
improves the Pareto frontier.
So each of these
models is better than--
given a method you can always
sweep this the size of the KV
cache by changing the K and the
head dimension, which, I guess,
kind of relates to your point
about changing model dimension.
But if you do this CLA cross
layer attention, it's better.
So moving on, whirlwind
tour of different techniques
for reducing KV cache.
There's a local or
sliding window attention.
This is a fairly
kind of old idea
and a very kind of natural idea.
So if you look at the
full attention matrix,
it's N squared.
And instead of doing
that, if you're
going to generate a token, you
just look at the last K tokens.
So you essentially
have a sliding window.
For every token you generate,
you just depend on the last K.
And now, if you do
that, the effective--
so the KV cache is now
independent of the sequence
length.
It's just the number of the
batch times the other variables,
which is great.
And this is especially
great for long context.
Now, because of the
number of layers,
the effective context
length is actually
larger than the number of
the stated context length
because information can
propagate farther in
if you go down the layers.
Now, you can do fancier things.
You can maybe not do a
dense selection of layers,
but you can space it out.
You can also do this
global plus sliding window
where aware you have
attention to a fixed
grid of different token points,
plus a local sliding window.
So you can do various things.
Now, the problem with
this is that it actually
still hurts accuracy.
So this reduces expressivity.
There's no free lunch
here, or at least this
was an expensive lunch.
So the solution that
people come up with
is that they interleave local
attention with global attention.
So these hybrid models have full
attention for some of the layers
and some local layers for
some of the other layers.
And you're basically
always trying
to-- and then so that allows
you to essentially reduce
the KV cache a little bit.
And you're always trying to
balance accuracy with the speed.
Yeah.
Hybrid model-wise,
is there a difference
between the trade-off in
using a linear time invariant
versus a sliding window?
Yeah.
So the question is, what about
linear attention versus sliding
window attention?
So I'm not going to talk
about linear attention.
But very quickly, there's a
bunch of methods that where,
instead of storing KV
cache, since you basically
compute some of compressed
representation of all
the history.
So linear, the most
naive linear attention
is you just sum the KV values
up into a single vector.
So that's definitely independent
of the sequence length.
You can do fancier things.
There's gated net,
delta nets, and Mamba
which allows you to try to
compress but not forget as much.
Now the question is,
how do those compare?
Those have also
been used in place
of sliding window attention, and
people have gotten good results
with them.
You can also use a
combination of full attention,
sliding window intention,
and the linear attention
because they capture
different aspects.
If you care about local
high-resolution stuff,
then sliding attentions better.
If you just want broad
summaries of the past,
then the other linear
attention might be better.
So then for a long
context sentence,
would you say your
attention would
be a better setting for that?
So the question is, for long
context with linear attention
be better?
So there's no free lunch, right?
Let's say you have
a very long context,
and you're solving a needle
in a haystack problem.
If you have to compress
your entire history
into a small context, you're
just going to lose information,
and you might just not
be able to retrieve it.
I guess I feel like what
it seems like people
go with hybrid architectures
that you'll always
need some of longer
attention, but I'm just
trying to understand in my head,
what the trade-off between using
a sliding window versus some
of a Mamba, delta net layer
would be.
Is using a delta
net layer better
than using sliding
window consistently?
Or what is the actual maybe
representative trade-offs?
Yeah.
Maybe I'll say that
the Mamba and delta net
are more powerful than
the sliding window.
Attention maybe you can
think about the Mamba
as probably can--
it certainly can represent some
of the aspects of sliding window
attention because you can just--
as you're doing the recurrence,
it can just look
at the last state.
So yeah, maybe you can think
about the linear attention
or its extensions
as being better.
They have more room.
Once you do sliding window
attention, you're done.
There's nothing else you can--
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
OK.
So let me just quickly
go through this.
Just highlight this DeepSeek.
DeepSeek continues to innovate
different types of attention
mechanisms.
So remember, they came up with
the multi-latent attention,
which compresses the key values.
There is this thing called--
now they have compressed
sparse attention, DeepSeek
sparse attention, and
heavily compressed attention.
I never remember all these
acronyms and what they mean,
but let's look at this diagram.
So normally, have your KV
tokens and your query token.
So compressed attention is
going to basically compress
every M tokens into one token.
And then there's
this thing called
DeepSeek sparse attention,
which basically selects
a subset of those to keep.
And the way you select a
subset is that you actually
compute some LiDAR
weight queries and keys,
and then you do a
smaller attention
to get these index scores
so you know to keep.
So a lightning fast
way to figure out
what tokens you need to keep.
And then you use those.
And then, there's some more
compression that happens.
So in the interest of
time, I'll move on.
The goal of this section is to
reduce the KV cache because KV
cache is related to memory.
And we saw that inference
is memory-bound.
So that directly
translates to improvements
in throughput and latency.
And the key is to do this
without hurting accuracy.
So you can do lower dimensional
KV caches across layers
by across heads and
across head dimension.
You can do local attention.
You can do linear attention,
which was discussed earlier,
and there's much more.
And there's also
diffusion models,
which is a
non-autoregressive way
to generate which
can be much faster.
OK.
So let's talk about a few other
ideas which are important.
So quantization is
more of a, I would
say, less of a
architecture and much more
of a systems of perspective
on how to make things smaller.
So the key idea here is just
reduce the precision of numbers.
Less memory means higher
latency and throughput.
And obviously, you have
to worry about accuracy.
So quantization is-- there's
many options here all the way
from bf16 all the
way down to int4.
And so one thing you
can do, if you're
scared that quantization
is going to mess you up,
is that you train a model
with quantization in mind.
So this is quantization
aware training.
And during the feedforward
pass during training,
you quantize and dequantize,
and you're basically
simulating these quantization
errors as you train.
So then, generally,
now the weights
are adapted towards
quantization.
Things will work better.
But the con is that it requires
expensive large-scale training.
And so what typically people
do is they train models,
and then they quantize
after the fact.
So this is post-training
quantization.
It's much cheaper often.
There's a naive way to do it is
that for every layer or tensor,
you basically determine the
scale and the 0 point for each,
let's say, tensor.
And then you quantize
that separately.
This generally
doesn't work as well.
You can use this
idea called GPTQ,
which uses some Hessian
information to quantize layer
by layer.
And then you keep track of the
errors which get propagated
into the non-quantized weights.
And so it allows you to
correct for the errors.
And now, activation-aware
quantizing
is more of a sophisticated
way where the observation is
that some activation
channels are large
and those the weights that
interact with those matter more.
So let's allocate more
precision to these weights.
So let's look at this picture.
So normally, if you
take fp16 weight matrix,
and you quantize it,
you get-- let's say
you quantize it down to int3.
But what you're going
to do is you figure out
which of these are active?
So these are maybe
activation channels.
And some of these activation
channels are large.
So if they're large
in general, then you
basically allocate like, let's
say, fp16 for this channel.
You keep everything
else as in three.
And for a few
important channels,
you use higher precision.
So another idea here
is to do model pruning.
So here you just
take a large model,
and you rip out pieces
of it, and you fix it up.
It's a very crude way,
but it turns out to work.
So there's this paper from
NVIDIA where, essentially--
let me actually-- let's see.
So you first have to
estimate the importance
of the different
parts of the model
and choose the most
important parts.
And then you basically
remove different hidden units
and different even layers.
And now, we have a model.
It's not going to be very good.
And so what you do
is you post-train it.
You train it some more
on the data or the tasks
that you care about to heal it.
So this is, in some sense, a
training way to reduce the KV
cache, but where you initialize
it with parts of a good model.
So this seems to
work pretty well.
So they were able to take a 15B
model and reduce it to an 8B
model.
And it doesn't really
hurt accuracy by too much.
And the amount that you
use to train the model
or through this
process is much less.
OK.
So just to summarize
here, the game
is to reduce the
inference complexity
without hurting accuracy.
You can think about this as
mostly reducing the number
of parameters or CPU cache.
You can define a faster model
architecture to train it,
or you can define a
faster model architecture.
Initialize the weights
from original model, which
might have a different
architecture,
but you just make this
Frankenstein thing,
and then you repair the faster
model with distillation.
OK.
Yeah.
Could you say more about you
distinguish the important
from the unimportant layers?
So how do you distinguish
the important layers
from the unimportant layers?
So in general, you
have a calibration set,
and you pass the inputs
through the model.
And you're basically
looking at the magnitude
of the activations.
And the ones that
are-- some of them,
especially if
they're dead units,
will be kind of close to 0.
And the ones that are
large, you want to keep.
So that's a high-level idea.
I guess why does it matter
if the activation is high?
It could just be
like-- what if it's
just always high, for instance?
Or is that--
So the question is, what if
all the activations are high?
So in general, this is a kind
of an empirical observation
that some of the channels will
be much higher than others.
If this weren't true, then these
techniques wouldn't necessarily
work, but it happens to
be true because that's
how these models ended
up being trained.
And then you can exploit that.
Say a neuron, which
is always value
100 across all the samples.
Would that mean that it's
necessarily meaningful?
Or maybe it's just an
artifact of training
that I'm just like [INAUDIBLE]?
Yeah, I see.
So the question is, what
if a neuron is always 100?
I mean, if that's the
case, you can also look
at variance-related questions.
If it's 100, you
can't just remove it
because then everything
is going to be broken.
If it's high mean
and low variance,
maybe there's another a way
to just incorporate the bias
essentially.
OK.
Let me quickly go
through this other idea.
So far, we've looked at
lossy methods which basically
really crunch down the KV cache,
but it could hurt accuracy.
This is a very elegant way of
doing this in a lossless way.
This is called speculative
sampling or speculative
decoding.
So remember that if
you're doing prefill,
you can encode all the
tokens in parallel.
This also gives
you probabilities.
This is fast.
This is compute-bound
and all nice things.
And in generation,
it's one at a time.
So checking is faster
than generation.
If I give you a sequence,
it's fast to tell me
how good it is, much faster than
it is to generate one at a time.
So you can exploit
this asymmetry
using the following idea.
So what we're going to do
is use a cheap draft model
to basically generate from
the guest a few tokens,
let's say four tokens.
And then we're going to use the
model we actually care about,
the target model Q, which to
basically review these tokens
and accept or not accept them.
So things are kind of
chosen to be balanced.
The draft model is just
smaller and cheaper.
And so even though
it's memory-bound,
and it has to generate one
at a time, is not too bad.
Whereas, the target model
is big and expensive,
but what we're
doing is asking it
to process a batch
of tokens in parallel
so it won't also be too bad.
OK, so here's the video
that shows how things work.
So if you use a big
model token by token,
it's going to be pretty slow.
But if you are doing
speculative decoding,
then you can see the small model
generating a bunch of tokens,
and then the large model
basically critiquing them.
And then, so you basically
can get this burst
of tokens and then maybe
another burst of tokens
and so on and so forth.
OK.
So here is the
algorithm for-- there's
a few papers that came out
with speculative decoding
around the same time.
This is one of them.
And so the idea here is
that in order to generate,
we're going to
generate K tokens.
And we're just going to
sample from this draft model.
So p is the draft model.
We're going to sample K tokens.
And then in
parallel, we're going
to compute the logits of
these draft tokens using q.
And then now we
have to determine
whether we accept or not.
And this is where you do a
bit of math and probability
and statistics.
You basically are going to
accept with probability Min 1
over this ratio of q over p.
So if q is much larger than
p, the larger the q is,
the more likely you
want to accept it.
And otherwise you sample from
this residual distribution
and exit.
So this is basically
rejection sampling
except for rejection sampling.
Sometimes when you
reject you get nothing.
But here we always
are guaranteed
to get an exact sample
from the target model.
I'm going to skip
this simple proof.
It's basically
the same arguments
as rejection sampling
to show that it's
the exact probabilities
from the target model.
And the initial paper
shows that this fast.
And generally, if you
have too few draft tokens,
you're not really leveraging
the batching on the target model
side.
And if you have too
many, then you're
going to reject more often.
So there's a sweet spot around,
in this case, three or four.
And in general, the draft
model is much smaller
than the target model.
And ideally, you want
the model draft model
to be as close to
the target, which
means that you
want to distill it,
which means that actually a lot
of the same ideas that we just
talked about are applicable to
speculative decoding as well.
So basically, the
idea is that let's try
to reduce your KV cache via
all the different shenanigans.
And if you end up with a
model you're happy with,
just serve that.
If you're not
happy with it, then
it at least can be a draft model
and you can use your main model
to fix things up.
There's a bunch of
whole literature
on speculative
decoding right now
that improve over the original,
which I'll skip for now.
So very quickly now,
dynamic workloads.
So this is the use case, is
you're serving a live website,
and users come and
chat with your model.
The requests arrive
at different times.
They have different
shared prefixes,
and they have different lengths.
So it's kind of pretty messy.
It's far from this very
simple training where
you have these blocks of
the same number of tokens
all at once.
So what do you do in this case?
So there's this idea--
there's a system called
Orca that was built.
This is actually
very early on which
introduced this idea
of continuous batching.
So the idea is that you
get a bunch of requests
that look like this.
So here's a prefix
of the first request,
and you're generating
this token.
Here's the second one.
Here's the third
one, the fourth one.
It's jagged because every
prefix has a different length.
And what we're
going to do is we're
going to decode step by step.
So every step you decode one
token for all the sequences.
Next step, you decode another
And then if you end, you
just eject that sequence.
And then as new requests
arrive to the batch,
then you basically
put it in the batch,
and then you just continue.
So that's why it's called
continuous batching because it's
this batch is
dynamically being updated
with either old finished
sequences being evicted
and new ones coming in.
So now, one problem
here is that everything
we've seen batching works
when all the sequences have
the same dimensionality.
You have tensors.
Every slice has the
same dimensionality.
But if you request here
has a different length,
so what do you do about that?
So there's this idea
called selective batching
where let's say you have a
length 3, length 9, and a length
5.
So here in the
attention computation,
you can't really do
anything about this
because attention depends on
the length of your sequence.
So if you have a 3 by
3, a 9 by 9 computation,
you can't really share
the tensor effectively.
But for the non-attention,
the MLP layers,
which takes up a lot of
FLOPs, you can actually just
concatenate all the
sequences together
to form a mega sequence,
and you process that.
So final idea is page attention.
This was introduced
in the BLM paper.
Of course, BLM has many
other bells and whistles now,
but this is the core
idea at that time.
So the question is, how
is the KV cache stored?
So if you think about
requests coming in,
you have to put them
in memory somewhere.
And in general,
there's this problem
that you get fragmentation.
This is what happens to--
or used to happen
to your hard drive.
And you have to defrag your
hard drive back in the day.
So there's two types
of fragmentation.
One is that you have to
allocate enough buffer so
that-- because you don't
when you're going to stop.
So you might have a max
token limit of 1,024.
So you have to allocate
all this memory.
And you can't put
anything in there
because you're going
to just generate
until you hit the max tokens,
and that's very wasteful.
That's internal fragmentation.
And then there's also you
have-- there could be space
between different requests.
And that space is maybe too
small to get used effectively.
So that's just wasted space.
So the solution here is just
these are systems people.
So they know their
operating systems.
They said, OK, well we've
solved this problem once before,
so let's just use
the same idea here.
So we're going to divide
the KV cache of a sequence
into non-contiguous blocks, OK?
So if you have this sequence,
four score and seven years
ago our fathers
brought forth, we're
just going to chunk it up
into these blocks of size 4.
Doesn't matter where the
blocks go, but they're
going to be aligned
according to the block.
So there's some
uniformity there.
So when two requests
share the same--
can actually share
the same KV cache.
So you might have this
block and this block.
So this block might
go here and here,
and this block
might be over there.
So they're interspersed.
But as long as you
have the indices
and keep track of where
everything is, it's fine.
So in particular, if you
have, system prompts, then
you can actually just
cache these system prompts,
the KV cache and the
system prompts, once.
And that can be useful
for all the queries, OK?
So this is very useful
because if a lot of people
are using the same
system prompt,
then you don't have to compute
the cache for every request.
Also there are many applications
where you have the same prompt,
and you actually want to
generate multiple responses.
So in that case, you
can also just share
the KB cache for
the prompt and just
have unique
responses coming out.
OK, So for example, if
you were to generate,
let's say, multiple
generations from score
and seven years ago are, blank,
and so what would happen here
is that you would
have score and seven.
And you would start by
having years ago or our.
And then this is called
copy on write semantics.
You keep this.
And then we have
these two samples.
And if they had happened to
sample let's say the same token,
you just continue with that.
But if they sample different
tokens, you split the block,
and then you can continue there.
So you're basically sharing
as much of the prefix cache
as you can.
There's a bunch of other
optimizations like kernels
that I'm not going to
have time to go over.
But the general
idea is that you're
using these operating
systems metaphors to manage
your inference.
So summary here-- inference
is really, really important.
It's very different
from training.
Even though it's the same model,
but you're asking the model
to do something very different,
ends up being very memory-bound.
And it's also dynamic if you're
in a live chatbot use case.
We saw a variety of different
techniques to improve inference.
You can quantize.
You can come up with
new architectures.
You can prune and distill.
You can also use
speculative sampling.
But all of these are driven
by the same principle
here, which is
reduce your KV cache
but don't hurt
accuracy too much.
And then there's ideas
from systems like paging
and speculative
execution that can
be brought to bear for actually
live inference servers.
One thing we didn't really
get a chance to talk about,
which was discussed
briefly, is that I
think that new architectures
have actually a huge potential
for improvement, things
like state space models
or linear attention
or diffusion.
At some level, the
KV cache and the way
that attention is
built fundamentally
makes it an inference
unfriendly kind of architecture.
So if you can come up with
a new architecture that
is designed for
inference in the way
that the transformer was not,
this can maybe unlock a lot.
OK, so I will stop there.
And next class, Tatsu
will return and talk
about scaling laws part 2.